Guide to the Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian and Gay Studies, Yale University, Exhibit and Research Materials from The Pink and The Blue
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian and Gay Studies, Yale University, exhibit and research materials from The Pink and The Blue
1827-2004
RU 963
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13.25
10 boxes
628.73
The materials consist of research files and exhibit panels relating to The Pink and the Blue: Lesbian and Gay Life at Yale and in Connecticut, 1642-2004, an exhibit produced by the Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian and Gay Studies at Yale. The research files consist primarily of duplicated material, however, some original writings, photographs, and memorabilia documenting Yale's lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender community are also included.
Yale University. Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian and Gay Studies
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 14-B (YRG 14-B), Records of academic departments and programs of the Yale Faculty of Arts and Sciences.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were transferred from the Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian and Gay Studies Coordinator, 2004. Additional donor information provided at the file level.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 8 is closed to research.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by subject and material type.
Biographical / Historical
The Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian and Gay Studies at Yale was founded in 2002 with a gift by Arthur Kramer in honor of his brother, author and activist Larry Kramer. The initiative supports the lesbian and gay community at Yale University through academic programs including lectures, conferences and symposia, special events, and community building activities.
In 2004, the Larry Kramer Initiative produced a major exhibition, The Pink and the Blue: Lesbian and Gay Life at Yale and in Connecticut, 1642-2004. In addition to conducting research, the Initiative staff solicited and received donations of material related to Yale's lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender history from Yale alumni and staff.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of research files and exhibit panels relating to The Pink and the Blue: Lesbian and Gay Life at Yale and in Connecticut, 1642-2004, an exhibit produced by the Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian and Gay Studies at Yale. The research files consist primarily of duplicated material, however, some original writings, photographs, and memorabilia documenting Yale's lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender community are also included.
Exhibitions; Gay and lesbian studies; Gay college students; Gay men -- Connecticut -- History; Homosexuality and education; Lesbians -- Connecticut -- History; Male homosexuality -- Connecticut -- History; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University -- Employees; Yale University. Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian and Gay Studies
- Research Files
  Scope and Contents
  The research files consist of bibliographical references, copies from articles, books and manuscripts, research notes, correspondence, manuscripts and memorabilia.
  Arrangement
  The research files are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Connecticut Colony sodomy law, 1830, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Plaine, William, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Fiske, John Stafford, 1827-1837 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Smashups" at Vassar, 1873, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lind, Earl, 1918-1922 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wilde, Oscar, at Yale, 1882, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mascolo v. Montesanto, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Porter, Cole, 1911-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12 - 13)
  - Rubineau, Angela Joan, Lesbian, Bisexual, and Gay Graduates of the Yale School of Medicine and Their Heterosexual Peers: Attitudes and Experiences, 1969-1998 (thesis), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - First Yale courses on homosexuality, descriptions of, 1973-1978, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Includes a short historical sketch by J. D. McClatchy of the 1973 seminar, the Literature of Ambiguity.
  - Ralph, Gary, essay on Yale experiences, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Gary Ralph, 2003
  - Dunlap, David, "The Yale of My Day: Chronicling a Cauldron", 1975 and 1997 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Boswell, John, Christianity, Social Tolerance and Homosexuality, newspaper clippings, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Gay at Yale, 1965-2001 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Oversize (Box 9)
  - Gay Alliance at Yale, Undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - The First Years of Yale's Gay and Lesbian Co-op, newspaper clippings, 1977-1993 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - First Gay and Lesbian Awareness Days, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Oversize, 1987-1992 (Box 10)
  - Yale's Gay and Lesbian Alumni Association Places First Ad in Yale Alumni Magazine, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Rustin, Bayard arrested leading demonstration, 1984-1998 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Includes a photograph of arrest, a proclamation, and an honorary degree from Yale.
  - Franklin, Kris and Sarah Chinn coordinators of Bisexual, Gay and Lesbian Awareness Day (BGLAD), photograph, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Lesbian and Gay Studies Organized at Yale, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Consists of flyers, a poster, and listing of courses relevant to lesbian and gay studies.
  - "Gay voices," Yale Daily News, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Documenting Discrimination, Prohibiting Discrimination, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - The Wayne Dick Controversy, newspaper clippings, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Wall Street Journal, "Lipsticks and Lords" article and Yale response, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - The Dobbs Incident at the Gay and Lesbian Studies Conference
    - Flyers, posters, and newpaper clippings, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 47 - 48)
    - Witness reports, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted
  - Van Vechten's Secret Scrapbooks, 1994 and 2003 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - New Haven Prohibits Sexual Orientation Discrimination/ Michael Morand, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Includes a photograph, newsclipping, and bills.
  - AIDS Activist Protest on Yale Campus, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Herek, Gregory, "Sexual Orientation and Prejudice at Yale: A Report on the Experiences of Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Members of the Yale Community" and "Documenting Prejudice Against Lesbians and Gay Men on Campus: The Yale Sexual Orientation Survey", 1986 and 1993 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - "Statement of Position: For the Inclusion of Sexual Orientation in the University's Equal Opportunity Statement, Circa 1990 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Connecticut Passes Gay Rights Bill, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - House of Safari Absolut, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Consists of an article in the New Journal that describes House of Safari Absolut, a group of primarily black, Yale and New Haven individuals.
  - The Murder of Matthew Shepard, articles from the Yale Daily News, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Yale Hosts Jewish LGBT Conference, flyer and program, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Yale Hosts Queer People of Color Conference, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Consists of a conference program for "Beyond Visibility: Queer People of Color Shattering Single Issue Politics."
  - Cohen, Cathy, photographs, undated; 3 computer files (TIFF)
    General note
    Contact Public Services (phone: 203 432-1735, e-mail: mssa.reference@yale.edu) for information on accessing this digital object.
  - Larry Kramer Initiative, founding of, 1997-2003 (Box 3, Folder 59-60)
    Includes newpaper and article clippings, and flyers for events sponsored by the Larry Kramer Initiative.
    - Oversize, 2003-2004 (Box 9)
  - Photographs of Larry Kramer Initiative events [?], Circa 2001-2003 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Unused (?) research materials
    - Fry, C. C., copies from Fry Papers, 1942-1948 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Articles on gay, lesbian, bisexual, and transgender topics, 1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Books and Yale Daily News Magazine, 1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Gay and Lesbian Alumni, poster, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Lesbian and Gay Faculty and Staff (Association Yale), 1986-1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Restricted until 2029
    - Johnson, Jimmy, Death of Liza Minnelli (play), 2003 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Yale Outlaws, photographic collage supporting gay marriage, 2003 (Box 10)
- Promotional materials, press clippings and comment book, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 66)
- Materials used in exhibition
  - Buttons, Undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - T-shirts (displayed in exhibition?), Circa 1979-2000 (Box 4–5)
  - Mounted panels, 2004 (Box 6–7)
- "The Pink and the Blue" brochure and poster, 2004; Computer files (multiple formats) (Box 11–12)
  Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
  - Oversize, 2004 (Box 9)